Register of the John Dickey Montgomery papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John Dickey Montgomery papers
1946-1991
75039
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes (7.5 linear feet)
Writings, reports, notes, interview summaries, and printed matter relating to American aid to South Vietnam and other southeast Asian countries, economic development in various Asian and African countries, Japanese and German public opinion regarding the purge of wartime leaders after World War II, and political, social, and economic effects of the purge on Japan and Germany.
Montgomery, John D. (John Dickey), 1920-2008.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual or digital material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975, with incremental material received in subsequent years.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1920 February 15 Born, Evanston, Illinois
1941 B.A., Kalamazoo College
1948 M.A., Harvard University
1951 Ph.D., Harvard University
1953 Author, Purge in Occupied Japan
1957 Author, Forced to be Free
1957-1959 Chief Academic Advisor, National Institute of Administration, Saigon, Vietnam
1959 Author, Cases in Vietnamese Administration
1961 Co-author, Education and Training in Developing Countries and Traditions, Values and Socio-Economic Development
1962 Author, The Politics of Foreign Aid
1963- Professor of Public Administration, Harvard University
1966 Author, Approaches to Development: Politics, Administration and Change
1969 Co-author, Political and Administrative Development
1974 Author, Technology and Civic Life, Making and Implementing Development Decisions
1975 Co-author, Policy Science and Population
1976 Co-author, Values and Development: Appraising Asian Experience
1979 Co-author, Patterns of Policy: Comparative and Longitudinal Studies of Population Events
1980 Co-author, Appropriate Technology and Social Values
1980- Chairman, Department of Government, Harvard University
1981 Co-author, Technology and International Affairs
1986 Author, Aftermath: Tarnished Outcomes of American Foreign Policy
1991- Director, Pacific Basin Research Center, Soka University of America
1995 Editor, with Dennis A. Rondinelli, Great Policies: Strategic Innovations in Asia and the Pacific Basin
1997 Editor, Values in Education: Social Capital Formation in Asia and the Pacific
1998 Editor, Human Rights: Positive Policies in Asia and the Pacific Rim
1999-2001 Editor, Policy Sciences
2001 Editor, with Alex Inkeles, Social Capital as a Policy Resource
2008 April 3 Died, Newton, Massachusetts
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, reports, notes, interview summaries, and printed matter relating to American aid to South Vietnam and other southeast Asian countries, economic development in various Asian and African countries, Japanese and German public opinion regarding the purge of wartime leaders after World War II, and political, social, and economic effects of the purge on Japan and Germany.
Denazification.; Economic assistance, American--Southeast Asia.; Economic assistance, American--Vietnam.; Land tenure--Vietnam.; Political purges--Germany.; Political purges--Japan.; Public opinion--Germany.; Public opinion--Japan.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Germany.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Japan.; Southeast Asia--Economic conditions.; Vietnam--Economic conditions.; Economic development.; Developing countries.; Africa--Economic conditions.; Asia--Economic conditions--1945-; Military government.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Germany--History--1945-1955.
- Buddhism. Instruction, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Burma
  - General
    - Notes, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Printed matter, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Statistics, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Customs. Instruction, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Economy. Project, reports, statistics, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Economy -- Finance. Memorandum, printed matter, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Foreign aid
    - Ford Foundation. Printed matter, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - USSR. Notes, report, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - U.S. government. Announcement, press release, report, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Foreign relations. Printed matter, summary of article, survey, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Rangoon. Printed matter, report, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Cambodia
  - General
    - Notes, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Statistics, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Fisheries. Notes, report, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - U.S. aid. Notes, printed matter, report, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 1: 16)
- Economic growth -- Rostow Thesis. Table, undated (Box-folder 1: 17)
- Germany. U.S. Zone -- Denazification. Charts, statistics, 1945-1949 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Japan
  - General. Notes, 1952 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Government
    - Composition. Statistics, 1935-1950 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Diet
      - First Session. Laws (translation of titles), 1947 (Box-folder 2: 4)
      - House of Representatives -- election. Tables (Japanese originals and translations), 1946 (Box-folder 2: 5)
      - House of Representatives -- election. Clippings, statistics, tables, 1952 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - National Opinion Research Institute. Report, survey, 1951 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Industrial organizations. List of titles, 1952 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Political parties. Comments, table, 1952 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Purge
    - Agencies
      - Attorney General's Office. Law (Japanese original and translation), 1947 (Box-folder 2: 10)
      - Attorney General's Office. Special Examining Bureau
        - Composition, structure, functions. Reports (Japanese originals and translations), 1952 (Box-folder 2: 11)
        - Procedure. Directives, instructions, laws, memoranda (Japanese originals and translations), 1948-1952 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
      - Screening committees. Review (translation), 1952? (Box-folder 3: 3)
      - Screening Organ. Statistics, statutes, tables, 1947? (Box-folder 3: 4)
      - Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers. General Headquarters. Directives, memoranda, reports, 1946 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Conduct and effects
      - General
        - Report, 1950 (Box-folder 3: 6)
        - Reports (Japanese), 1951-1952 (Box-folder 3: 7-8)
        - Statistics and records (Japanese originals and translations), 1948-1951 (Box-folder 3: 9)
      - Bureaucracy. Interview, statistics, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 3: 10)
      - Communist Party. Statement, directive (Japanese original and translation), 1952? (Box-folder 3: 11)
      - Diet. List of names, reports, statistics (Japanese originals and translations), 1952 (Box-folder 3: 12)
      - Economy
        - Plans for investigations, 1952? (Box-folder 3: 13)
        - Report on corporations, 1952? (Box-folder 3: 14)
        - Report on industry (Japanese original and translation), 1952 (Box-folder 3: 15-16)
        - Report on Zaibatsu Combines, 1953 (Box-folder 4: 1)
        - Statistics, 1952? (Box-folder 4: 2)
        - Summary of field research (Japanese original and translation), 1952 (Box-folder 4: 3-5)
      - Educational system
        - Report (translation), 1952 (Box-folder 4: 6)
        - Letter (Japanese), 1952? (Box-folder 4: 7)
      - Investigation. Study plan, 1952? (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - Prefectures. List of purgees, 1952 (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - Political parties. Report (Japanese original and translation), 1952 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
      - Purgees
        - Activities -- limitations. Report (translation), 1952 (Box-folder 5: 3-5)
        - Living conditions. Report (Japanese original and translation), 1949 (Box-folder 5: 6)
      - Right wing organizations. Report (Japanese original and translation), 1952 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Public comments
      - Mainichi Press. Collection of articles (translation), 1953 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
      - Newspapers. Clippings (Japanese), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - Public opinion poll
      - General. Letter, notes, questionnaires (Japanese originals and some translations), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 4)
      - Comparative investigation -- region differences among Osaka, Tokyo, and Yamagata. Report (Japanese original and translation), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 5)
      - Funagata. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 6)
      - Iizuka. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 7)
      - Interviewers
        - Biographic data (Japanese originals and some translations), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 8)
        - Instructions (Japanese originals and translations), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 9)
      - Nagano prefecture
        - General. Summary of investigations, 1952 (Box-folder 6: 10)
        - Goka. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 11)
        - Kamisato. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 6: 12)
        - Kitayama. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 7: 1)
        - Matsuo. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 7: 2)
        - Nakasu. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 7: 3)
        - Urasato. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      - Omuta. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 7: 5)
      - Osaka. Interviews, reports (Japanese), 1952 (Box-folder 7: 6)
      - Pre-pilot survey. Instruction, report (Japanese original and translation), summary, 1952 (Box-folder 7: 7)
      - Takanata. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 8: 1)
      - Tokyo. Statistics (Japanese), summary (Japanese original and translation), 1952 (Box-folder 8: 2-6)
      - Ueda. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 8: 7)
      - Yamagata. Interviews, reports (translations), 1952 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - U.S. policy. Report, typed copies of magazine and newspaper articles, 1948-1952 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Laos
  - General. Notes, printed matter, statistics, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - Government. Clipping, excerpt from book, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - U.S. aid. Notes, printed matter, reports, 1959 (Box-folder 9: 5)
- Thailand
  - General
    - Notes, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - Printed matter, 1959 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Economy. Notes, 1959? (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Economy -- Petchaboon Province. Survey, 1959 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Education. Printed matter, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - Government
    - General. Notes, report, 1958-1959? (Box-folder 9: 11)
    - Municipal administration. Decree, notes, 1952-1959? (Box-folder 9: 12)
    - Structure and composition. Charts, memorandum, notes, statement, statutes, 1954-1959 (Box-folder 9: 13)
    - Thai Technical and Economic Committee. Forms, notes, program, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Public health. Notes, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Public health -- Malaria Eradication Project. Notes, statement, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - U.S. aid
    - General. Letter, printed matter, report, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - U.S. Operations Mission to Thailand
      - General. Letters, notes, projects, reports, statistics, summary of contracts, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 5)
      - Structure and composition. Directory, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 6)
      - Sub-agencies
        - Community Development Advisor. Comments, report, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 10: 7)
        - Education Division. Notes, project, reports, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 10: 8)
        - Public Administration Division. Study, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 9)
        - Public Health Division. Reports, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 10: 10)
        - Public Works and Engineering Division. Projects, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 11)
- United States
  - Foreign Aid. Comments, law, minutes, project, reports, 1957-1960? (Box-folder 10: 12)
  - Foreign aid -- U.S. International Cooperation Administration. Airgrams, chart, forms, manual, orders, printed matter, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 10: 13)
  - Information Service. Daily wireless file, interview, notes, 1958 (Box-folder 10: 14)
- Vietnam
  - Bibliography, 1958 (Box-folder 10: 15)
  - Lecture on history, 1957 (Box-folder 10: 16)
- Vietnam, North -- land policy. Printed matter, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 17)
- Vietnam, South
  - General. Clipping (French), printed matter (Vietnamese), quotations from American press, reports, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 10: 18)
  - Civic Action Program. Interviews, memorandum, notes, press review, report, 1958 (Box-folder 10: 19)
  - Constitution and laws. Collection of decrees and laws, copy of constitution, 1958 (Box-folder 10: 20)
  - Economy
    - General. Notes, printed matter (French, Vietnamese), summary, 1958 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Agriculture
      - General. Interview, notes, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 11: 2)
      - Credits. Interviews, letters, memoranda, projects, reports, statements, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 11: 3)
      - Fertilizers. Notes, report, 1959 (Box-folder 11: 4)
      - Irrigation and drainage. Letter, notes, project, reports, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 11: 5)
      - Land reform
        - Laws, 1957 (Box-folder 11: 6)
        - Letter, 1959 (Box-folder 11: 7)
        - Notes, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 11: 8)
        - Printed matter, 1957 (Box-folder 11: 9)
        - Reports
          - Gittinger, J. Price, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 11: 10-13)
          - Ladejinski, W. I., 1955 (Box-folder 11: 14)
          - Wurfel, David, 1956 (Box-folder 11: 15)
          - U.S. Operations Mission to Vietnam, 1959 (Box-folder 11: 16)
        - Statistics, 1959 (Box-folder 11: 17)
      - Rice production. Interviews, memorandum, reports, review of press, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 11: 18)
      - U.S. Operations Mission to Vietnam. Airgram, interviews, report, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 11: 19)
      - U.S. State Department. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 11: 20)
      - Vietnam government. Instruction, interviews, notes, reports, 1958 (Box-folder 11: 21)
      - Vietnam government. Department of Land Registration and Land Reform. Proposal of reorganization, 1957 (Box-folder 11: 22)
    - Contractors. Instruction, notes, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 11: 23)
    - Energy. Excerpts from book, 1957 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Finance
      - General. Excerpts from book, minutes, notes, 1958 (Box-folder 12: 2)
      - Michigan State University. Vietnam Advisory Group. Interviews, memorandum, notes, reports, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 12: 3)
      - U.S. Operations Mission to Vietnam. Statistics, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Fishing and fish breeding. Letter, notes, reports, review of press, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Industry
      - General. Interviews, memorandum, news release, notes, proposals, report, review of press, 1958 (Box-folder 12: 6)
      - Investments. Comments (French), policy statements, 1957 (Box-folder 12: 7)
      - U.S. Operations Mission to Vietnam. Interview, notes, 1958 (Box-folder 12: 8)
      - Vietnam government. Industrial Development Center. Notes, press release, statement, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 12: 9)
      - Vietnam government. National Agricultural College. Letter, notes, reports, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 12: 10)
    - Trade
      - General. Clippings (Vietnamese original and translations), undated (Box-folder 12: 11)
      - Commercial import. Interviews, lists of items, notes, report, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 12: 12)
      - Freight
        - General. Laws, notes, review of press, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 12: 13)
        - U.S. Embassy. Memorandum, 1958 (Box-folder 12: 14)
        - U.S. International Cooperation Administration. Airgram, telegram, 1957 (Box-folder 12: 15)
        - U.S. Operations Mission to Vietnam. Airgrams, letters, memoranda, notes, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 12: 16)
        - Vietnam government. National Bank. Letter (French original and translation), 1958 (Box-folder 12: 17)
      - Vietnam government. Central Purchasing Agency. Charts, letters, notes, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 12: 18)
    - Transportation
      - General. Interview, letter, notes, program, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 12: 19)
      - Civil aviation. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 12: 20)
      - Highways. Interview, letters, notes, work description, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 12: 21)
      - Railroads. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 12: 22)
      - Waterways. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 12: 23)
    - United Nations. International Monetary Fund. Report (French), 1959 (Box-folder 12: 24)
  - Education
    - Interviews, 1958 (Box-folder 12: 25)
    - Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Reports, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - Government
    - Compensation practice. Memorandum, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - Foreign Aid Administration. Chart, notes, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Law enforcement agencies
      - General. Interview, reports, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 13: 5)
      - Notes, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 13: 6)
      - Press comments. Magazine articles, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 7)
      - Reform projects, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - National Assembly. Clippings, notes, review of press, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 13: 9)
    - National Committee for Community Development. Report, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 10)
    - National Institute of Administration. Chronology, letters, notes, statistics, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 13: 11)
    - National Institute of Administration -- academic activities. Charts, curricula. reports, statistics, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 12)
    - Presidency. Summary of lecture, undated (Box-folder 13: 13)
    - Structure. Charts, map, ordinance, review of press, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 13: 14)
  - Mass media. Review, undated (Box-folder 13: 15)
  - Michigan State University. Vietnam Advisory Group. Field Administration Division. Narrative history, 1959 (Box-folder 13: 16)
  - Political parties and political freedom. Statement, undated (Box-folder 13: 17)
  - Public health. Decrees, interviews, notes, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 13: 18)
  - Refugees. Circular, interviews, notes, reports, statement, statistics, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 13: 19)
  - U.S. aid
    - General. Airgram, critical remarks, interviews, memorandum, minutes, notes, printed matter, program, project agreement, radio broadcast, review of press, summary, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 13: 20)
    - U.S. Operations Mission to Vietnam
      - General
        - Interview, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 21)
        - Memoranda, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 22)
        - Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 14: 1)
        - Notices, 1958 (Box-folder 14: 2)
        - Orders, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 14: 3-5)
        - Panel discussions, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 14: 6-11)
        - Reports, 1958 (Box-folder 14: 12)
      - Administrative functions. Interviews, memoranda, notes, projects, 1958 (Box-folder 14: 13)
      - Relations
        - General. Interview, notes, 1958 (Box-folder 14: 14)
        - Private companies. Notes, table, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 14: 15)
        - U.S. Congress. Letter, list of Congressional visitors, memoranda, notes, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 14: 16)
        - U.S. Embassy. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 14: 17)
        - U.S. International Cooperation Administration. Interview, 1958 (Box-folder 14: 18)
        - Vietnam government. Interview, memoranda, notes, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 14: 19)
      - Structure and composition. Charts, directory, interview, list of names, notes, orientation program, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 14: 20)
      - Sub-agencies
        - Controller's Office. Interview, notes, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 15: 1)
        - Division of Agriculture and Natural Resources. Memoranda, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 15: 2)
        - Education Division. Chart, notes, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 3)
        - Executive Office. Interview, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 4)
        - Field Service Division
          - Project proposal, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 5)
          - Reports, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 15: 6-9)
        - Finance Division. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 10)
        - Health and Sanitation Division. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 11)
        - Information Service. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 12)
        - Program Support Division. Notes, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 13)
        - Public Administration Division. Chart, notes, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 14)
  - U.S. Embassy. Clippings, instruction, interview, list of names, 1958 (Box-folder 15: 15)
- Incremental Material (Boxes 16-18)
  Scope and Contents note
  Material not yet described.